<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/changes/1.0.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/changes/1.0.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/changes-1.0.0.xsd">
    <properties>
        <title>JGloss Changes</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <release version="2.1.1" date="not yet released">
            <action type="add">The JGloss web start files are now signed with an official certificate as "Open Source Developer, Michael Koch".</action>
            <action type="add">JGloss download files and Maven artefacts are now PGP signed.</action>
            <action type="add">Added home page links to help menu.</action>
        </release>
        <release version="2.1.0" date="2013-05-20">
            <action type="update">JGloss now requires at least Java 7.</action>
            <action type="add">Support for EDICT2 dictionary format.</action>
            <action type="update">The dictionary lookup dialog now performs searches immediately (no more search button).</action>
            <action type="add">Priority entries are now preferred for annotations.</action>
            <action type="add">An empty JGloss document now shows a panel with the most imporant actions.</action>
            <action type="add">Opening JGloss 1 documents is now supported.</action>
            <action type="update">Maven is now used for build and site generation.</action>
            <action type="removed">The search options are no longer stored in the preferences.</action>
            <action type="removed">Removed platex export templates. The Latex-CJK templates work just as well.</action>
            <action type="removed">Removed compact view option because it never worked properly.</action>
            <action type="fix">Fixed search history.</action>
            <action type="fix" due-to="Andreas Winter">Reduced ChaSen termination timeout to 1 second, because it doesn't terminate
                normally.</action>
            <action type="update" due-to="Andreas Winter">Don't change current selection on mouseclick in empty screen area.</action>
            <action type="add" due-to="Andreas Winter">View is automatically scrolled to show selected annotation.</action>
        </release>
        <release version="2.0 Alpha 3" date="2004-06-06">
            <action type="add">Support for UTF-8 encoded KANJIDIC dictionary files.</action>
            <action type="add">New option to import text without adding annotations.</action>
            <action type="update">Changed JGloss documentation format to XML Docbook.</action>
            <action type="update">Docbook XSL and FOP is now used for generation of documentation.</action>
            <action type="update">Ant is now used for builds.</action>
        </release>
        <release version="2.0 Alpha 2" date="2004-02-02">
            <action type="update">Changed dictionary format detection to work with more EDICT and WadokuJT versions.
            </action>
            <action type="add">Support for UTF-8 encoded EDICT files.</action>
            <action type="add">Explanation dialog for unrecognized dictionary formats.</action>
        </release>
        <release version="2.0 Alpha 1" date="2003-02-02">
            <action type="fix">Fixed JGloss startup with uninitialized prefs.</action>
            <action type="fix">Fixed HTML export.</action>
            <action type="add">Added LaTeX export.</action>
        </release>
        <release version="2.0 Alpha 0" date="2003-02-02">
            <action type="update">Extended dictionary functionality.</action>
            <action type="add">Document window now includes word lookup panel.</action>
            <action type="update">Annotated words are looked up when selected, not only during document import.</action>
            <action type="update">Redesign and rewrite of many internals.</action>
            <action type="update">Java2 1.3 is no longer supported, minimum version is 1.4.</action>
            <action type="fix">Some features from JGloss 1.0.x are still missing in this release.</action>

        </release>
        <release version="1.0.10" date="2004-06-06">
            <action type="add">support for UTF-8 encoded KANJIDIC dictionary files</action>
        </release>
        <release version="1.0.9" date="2004-04-04">
            <action type="fix">fixed index creation and search for EDICT-UTF8 dictionary format</action>
            <action type="fix">fixed ChaSen parsing bug</action>
        </release>
        <release version="1.0.8" date="2004-03-03">
            <action type="fix">fixed bug in dictionary loading which made the preferences window unuseable</action>
        </release>
        <release version="1.0.7" date="2004-02-02">
            <action type="update">changed dictionary format detection to work with more EDICT and WadokuJT versions.
            </action>
            <action type="add">support for UTF-8 encoded EDICT files (only with Java2 1.4).</action>
            <action type="add">explanation dialog for unrecognized dictionary formats.</action>
            <action type="remove">removed annotatehml startup option.</action>
        </release>
        <release version="1.0.6" date="2002-08-08">
            <action type="update">Improved keyboard navigation.</action>
            <action type="add">Added best match search option to word lookup.</action>
            <action type="add">Added automatic lookup of clipboard content to word lookup.</action>
            <action type="add">Added keyboard shortcut for Import Clipboard.</action>
            <action type="fix">Changed combo box in word lookup dialog to text field to work around a bug in the JRE
                1.4 Windows Look &amp; Feel. This fixes the need to push the "Search" button twice.</action>
            <action type="update">Changed GDICT name to WadokuJT.</action>
            <action type="fix">Fixed WadokuJT implementation regex which would hang JGloss for a few entries.</action>
            <action type="fix">Fixed access of A drive dialogs when using file dialogs with Windows and JRE 1.3.
            </action>
        </release>
        <release version="1.0.5" date="2002-06-06">
            <action type="update">Improved paragraph detection on text import.</action>
            <action type="add">Added XML export option.</action>
            <action type="fix">Fixed memory leak. Now all memory used by a document is released after the document
                window is closed.</action>
            <action type="fix">Fixed font size bug where occasionally the font size of the readings/translations would
                be wrong if no background color is selected.</action>
            <action type="fix">Fixed selection of KANJIDIC dictionaries in the word lookup dialog.</action>
        </release>
        <release version="1.0.4" date="2002-05-05">
            <action type="add">Added template-based LaTeX-export.</action>
            <action type="update">For long translations, a shorter translation entry is automatically added (mainly
                noticeable with GDICT).</action>
            <action type="add">Font and font size of word lookup result is now configurable.</action>
            <action type="add">Added font auto-configuration option to style settings.</action>
            <action type="fix">Bug fixes to GDICT entry parsing.</action>
            <action type="fix">Fixed reading generation for mixed Katakana-Kanji words.</action>
            <action type="fix">Fixed handling of infix ke which is read as ka in new annotation creation.</action>
            <action type="fix">Fixed font autodetection under J2SE 1.4.</action>
            <action type="fix">Fixed LaTeX export under J2SE 1.3.</action>
            <action type="fix">Fixed large result list in word lookup scrolls to end bug.</action>
        </release>
        <release version="1.0.3" date="2002-03-03">
            <action type="add">Added support for GDICT dictionaries (J2SE 1.4 required).</action>
            <action type="update">Reimplementation of EDICT using the NIO API (J2SE 1.4 required). Improved load time and
                decreased RAM usage.</action>
            <action type="add">Added escaping of characters not supported by EUC-JP to the user dictionary.</action>
            <action type="update">The document view will truncate long translations to improve the layout. This does not
                affect the length of translations in export formats.</action>
            <action type="fix">Fixed EDICT index creation and search bugs. To increase search accuracy you should
                delete all old .jjdx index files.</action>
            <action type="update">Rendering of the document pane is now done in the background.</action>
            <action type="update">Document rendering speed improvement for J2SE 1.4.</action>
            <action type="update">Decreased perceived startup time by deferring dictionary loading until after the main
                window is created.</action>
            <action type="fix">Better error handling when opening dictionaries.</action>
            <action type="update">Improved KanjiDic load time.</action>
            <action type="update">The annotation list dialog now defaults to the last used directory.</action>
            <action type="add">Use of J2SE 1.4 prefs API if available. Old .jgloss preference settings will be migrated
                automatically.
            </action>
        </release>
        <release version="1.0.2" date="2002-02-02">
            <action type="add">Annotation editor now remembers it's width.</action>
            <action type="fix">Fixes for J2SE 1.4 incompatibilities.</action>
            <action type="fix">Fixed all tree nodes are editable bug.</action>
        </release>
        <release version="1.0.1" date="2002-01-01">
            <action type="add">Added user interface font selection to style preference panel.</action>
            <action type="add">Font autodetection on first startup. JGloss tries to set reasonable default fonts
                depending on the system.</action>
            <action type="add">Added option to set the document title.</action>
            <action type="update">LaTeX export uses document title as page header.</action>
            <action type="add">Added a text field to the import dialog into which Japanese text can be pasted. This
                obsoletes the -p command line option, which is removed.</action>
            <action type="add">Added UTF-16 encodings to import encoding selection.</action>
            <action type="add">Keyboard shortcut: typing delete while an annotation node is selected clears the
                translation.</action>
            <action type="update">Katakana words are no longer annotated with hiragana readings when a word/reading is
                selected.</action>
            <action type="add">Last selected annotation is remembered between saves.</action>
            <action type="fix">Import Clipboard now works under X11.</action>
            <action type="fix">Fixed display of dictionary entries without readings in long word lookup results.
            </action>
            <action type="fix">Fixed button sizes in dictionary and exclusion list preferences.</action>
            <action type="fix">Fixed adding annotation with reading but no translation.</action>
            <action type="fix">Fixed saving of the preferences and user dictionary if the application is quit by other
                means than closing all windows.</action>
        </release>
        <release version="1.0" date="2001-12-12">
            <action type="update">Improved handling of long result lists in word lookup dialog.</action>
            <action type="remove">Removed the dummy print menu item from the word lookup dialog.</action>
            <action type="fix">Fixed exception thrown if the document window is closed while a document is loaded.
            </action>
            <action type="remove">Removed the "enable direct editing" entry from the preferences dialog since this feature
                is buggy and can break the document if not used with care. If you still want to use it, add the line
                "editor.enableeditingcheckbox=true" to the ".jgloss" preferences file.
            </action>
            <action type="update">Verb inflection in word lookup dialog will not be used any longer for hiragana-only
                search expressions.</action>
            <action type="update">Find dialog defaults to currently selected text.</action>
            <action type="add">Added file chooser icons for some file types.</action>
            <action type="add">LaTeX export can now alternatively put translations at the end of the document.</action>
            <action type="update">Improved LaTeX translation formatting.</action>
            <action type="remove">Removed character set selection from LaTeX export dialog, since platex does not work
                with all charsets. LaTeX export defaults to EUC-JP encoded files.</action>
            <action type="add">Word lookup window now remembers its size.</action>
            <action type="add">Left-clicking an annotated word now selects the annotation. This behavior can be changed
                in the preferences.</action>
            <action type="update">Style changes in the preferences are only applied once to open documents.</action>
            <action type="add">When annotating a word manually, the first reading and translation are now automatically
                selected.</action>
            <action type="fix">Fixed treatment of special characters /, @ and | in annotations when saving and loading
                documents.</action>
            <action type="update">Changed default font sizes.</action>
            <action type="add">Added Use Reading/Translation entry to annotation context menu.</action>
            <action type="add">Clicking in unannotated text now deselects the current annotation.</action>
            <action type="add">Delete key on a reading or translation node now clears the text.</action>
            <action type="fix">Dictionaries preferences now prevents adding the same dictionary file twice.</action>
            <action type="remove">Removed the Annotations Follow Mouse setting, since it no longer makes sense with the
                changes in the annotation editor behavior.</action>
            <action type="fix">Fixed display of reading in annotation popups.</action>
        </release>
        <release version="0.9.4" date="2001-11-11">
            <action type="update">Improved handling of reading annotations in imported text; ChaSen parser can now be used
                with texts with reading annotations.</action>
            <action type="update">Changed annotation editor to only expand tree for selected annotation. This speeds up
                document display and decreases memory usage.</action>
            <action type="add">Added find option.</action>
            <action type="add">Added open recent menu.</action>
            <action type="add">Input focus can be switched to annotation editor with TAB key.</action>
            <action type="fix">Fixed escaping of special characters in LaTeX export.</action>
            <action type="update">Enlarged text input fields in annotation editor.</action>
            <action type="fix">Fixes to JGloss-WWW.</action>
        </release>
        <release version="0.9.3" date="2001-09-09">
            <action type="add">Annotations can now have more than one reading. In a word with more than one kanji
                substring, a reading is added for every substring. Non-kanji substrings don't get a reading annotation.
            </action>
            <action type="update">Changed HTML generation. The generated HTML is now simpler, but may not work as well as
                previously with browsers which don't support ruby elements.</action>
            <action type="add">There are now two text parsers, the previous
                "Kanji" parser and a parser which uses the
                ChaSen morphological analysis tool.
            </action>
            <action type="add">Manual annotation addition now displays a dialog which lets you look up the annotation
                in the dictionaries before you add it.</action>
            <action type="fix">Fixed bug where the document would sometimes scroll to a different location if a
                reading/translation is changed.</action>
            <action type="fix">Fixed document name setting in save as.</action>
            <action type="fix">Fixed JJDX creation for dictionaries with more than 500.000 index entries.</action>
        </release>
        <release version="0.9.2" date="2001-08-08">
            <action type="add">Added dialog for looking up words in the dictionaries.</action>
            <action type="fix">Extreme speedup of EDICT lookups. The old entry match test was really broken.</action>
            <action type="update">Changed EDICT indexing algorithm. The new algorithm is faster and uses far less RAM.
            </action>
            <action type="add">Added French translation, contributed by Alexandre Beraud
                (currently incomplete).
            </action>
            <action type="add">Added paste import window. Text pasted in this window will be imported in a new JGloss
                document. This is mainly useful for working with the X primary selection. It is accessible with the -p
                command line option.</action>
            <action type="add">Added composite verb detection to parser.</action>
            <action type="add">Added user dictionary.</action>
            <action type="add">Added dictionary form node to annotation editor. This allows greater control over what
                will be written in LaTeX and annotation list exports.</action>
            <action type="add">Added "use for all" function.</action>
            <action type="add">HTML export: files now show reading and translation in popup windows in browsers which
                support the neccessary JavaScript functions, and in the status bar.</action>
            <action type="add">Added command line option -a, which annotates Japanese words in a HTML page with
                dictionary entries.</action>
            <action type="update">Creation of the preferences panel and loading of the dictionaries now happens in the
                background. This decreases the perceived startup time.</action>
            <action type="fix">Popup menus will be positioned to always fit on the screen.</action>
            <action type="add">A dialog will ask for confirmation before existing files are overwritten.</action>
            <action type="add">An extension will automatically be added to file names if no extension is given by the
                user.</action>
            <action type="add">Opening an already open document will bring the existing window to the front.</action>
            <action type="add">Added file format version numbering.</action>
            <action type="add">Added a JGloss servlet. The servlet proxies web pages and annotates them with Japanese
                translations.</action>
        </release>
        <release version="0.9.1" date="2001-07-07">
            <action type="add">Added support for KANJIDIC dictionaries.</action>
            <action type="add">Added support for SKK word-reading dictionaries.</action>
            <action type="add">Added command line option for dictionary format detection.</action>
            <action type="add">Added word exclusion list to automatic annotation.</action>
            <action type="add">Added index file format JJDX, which can be used instead of XJDX index files. JGloss will
                create the index if none is found.</action>
            <action type="add">Added command line options for JJDX creation and opening JGloss files.</action>
            <action type="add">Added command to remove duplicate annotations.</action>
            <action type="update">Improved HTML import. Still not very useful, though.</action>
            <action type="update">Speeded up initial display of documents. Unfortunately, it is still slow.</action>
            <action type="add">The annotation editor shows readings/translations for hidden annotations.</action>
            <action type="update">LaTeX: changed ruby size in ruby-annotation.sty</action>
            <action type="add">Hidden annotations are not expanded after a document is loaded.</action>
            <action type="fix">Fixed addition of space character when starting editing of readings or translations.
            </action>
            <action type="fix">Fixed apply button in preferences dialog not working.</action>
            <action type="fix">Fixed unchecking background color settings will not change colors.</action>
            <action type="fix">Fixed using 'n' to select next annotation expands hidden annotations.</action>
            <action type="fix">Fixed scrolling of document when using 'n'.</action>
            <action type="fix">Fixed cancel button when adding annotations manually.</action>
        </release>
        <release version="0.9" date="2001-06-06">
            <action type="add">Initial release.</action>
        </release>
    </body>
</document>